JOE: All individuals transition from
one activity to another and from
one setting to another every day, at
home, school, or in the workplace.
These may involve major
transitions or minor transitions.
Individuals with autism often find
it difficult to predict what is
happening in their day as well as
planning and executing transitions.
Transitions whether minor or major for
individuals with autism can be a stressful
and confusing process that often results
in emotional distress or disengagement.
BETH: Individuals with autism
spectrum disorders may have greater
difficulty in shifting attention
from one task to another or handling
changes of their routine or setting.
This may be due to a greater need
for predictability, challenges in
understanding what activity will be
coming next, or difficulty when a
pattern of behaviour is disrupted.
JOE: When transition strategies are
used, they can help with reducing
the amount of transition time and
improving appropriate behaviour
during transitions and disruptions
to activities, settings, or routines.
Strategies can be used before a
transition occurs, during a transition,
and after a transition, and can
be verbal, auditory, or visual.
They can help to increase
predictability for individuals on
the autism spectrum and to create
positive routines around transitions.
BETH: When looking at transitions there
are a number of strategies that can be
used to support individuals with autism.
Visual supports such as pictures
or real objects can indicate
what the transition may involve
and be can be used as a prompt.
Visual timers, digital alerts and day
planners can give prior notice and
warning when transitions may occur.
JOE: Preparing individuals for
transitions in advance though a range
of different methods can help them
become aware of what to expect and
making them part of that transition
by involving them in the process can
help them to feel more in control.
BETH: Making sure everyone concerned
is aware of the issues, can make things
more consistent in approach and detail,
so that they can reinforce any guidance
and support that might be needed.
Using these strategies and types
of supports can help prepare
children and adults to initiate
and carry out a transition and
to demonstrate the appropriate
behaviour relying less on prompting.